A Guide to the Correspondence of Charles Tenney with Adelaide Case, 1861-1863
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Correspondence of Charles Tenney with Adelaide Case, 1861-1863
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11616
This collection consists of ca. 150 correspondence items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift to the Library by Corrine Carr Nettleton of Charlottesville, Va. on May 5, 2000.
Biographical/Historical Information
Charles Tenney was a Union soldier in the Seventh Ohio Regiment.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of correspondence, ca. 150 items, 1861-1863, between Charles Tenney, a Union soldier from Ohio, and Adelaide Case, a friend from Mecca, Ohio, and three photographs. Tenney is a Private in Company H of the Seventh Ohio Regiment. The letters poignantly show the development of the romance between the two as Tenney participates in numerous engagements during the Civil War.
Arrangement
These letters are arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Charles Tenney Letters, 1861-1863, 62 letters
  - Charles Tenney Letters, 1861, 13 letters
    Thirteen letters in 1861 detail Tenney's early days in the war, some aboard the U.S. Steamer "Silver Lake" as it traverses points along the Ohio River. They include a vivid description of Piatt's (Abraham Sanders) Zouaves, descriptions of the countryside, a variety of interesting pictorial stationary, a hanging and military movements. The end of 1861 finds him in Hampshire County, Va., near Romney.
    - Camp Denison, Ohio, June 6, 1861
      In a letter, Tenney says his camp is pleasant, and he would like Addie to visit him, but particularly he would like her to think of him as more than just a friend.
    - On Board U.S. Steamer Silver Lake on Ohio River, September 9, 1861
      Tenney is en route to Cincinnati. In his letter, he says on board are several wounded from battle of Carnifex Ford and the remains of Col. [ ]Lowe, of the 12th Ohio Regiment, who fell in battle. Tenney describes feelings while engaged in battle at [Coop Lanes] and mentions beauty of the countryside. He also tells of meeting a steamer loaded with Piatt's Zouave Brigade.
    - Unidentified location, September 17, 1861
      Tenney tells of an uprising by the 13th and 10th Ohio Regiments due to "too much whiskey" and the participation of the 7th in quelling it; thirteen men badly wounded and several bruised and badly frightened.
    - On Board Silver Lake, September 24, 1861
      Tenney is on guard duty. He thinks the Kanawha Valley is the most beautiful he has seen and thinks it is a sacrilege" the war will deform it. Tenney also gives a vivid description of passing the charred remains of the Confederate steamer "Julia Moffit" and of the circumstances that sank it. He says he will be glad when the war is over as it is like "hitting friends," but he writes that he believes firmly in continuing his duty.
    - Charleston, Va. (W. Va.), October 1, 1861
      Tenney writes that the valley has become quiet, so he is off the boat. He describes severe flooding in Charleston with river swelling because of heavy rains; he says the whole town like a "little Venice." Tenney tells of an instance where he went to aid of "Secesh" woman whose entire house and furnishings were ruined with "the more superstitious thinking the flood was a judgment on the South for engaging in the war."
    - Camp at Charleston, Va. October 6, 1861
      Tenney describes a hanging in Charleston of a Nimrod Bailey, keeper of a lager beer saloon, who shot a soldier who had been making a disturbance in the saloon. Tenney thinks the entire trial and hanging was premature. He also says everyone is having a fine time in Charleston gathering souvenirs of Southern "hospitality."
    - Illegible letter October 10, 1861
      This is a largely illegible letter in which Tenney appears to be discussing the war's strategy.
    - Charleston, October 16, 1861
      Tenney tells of being inspected by Maj. Stemmer (Adam Jacoby) who he thinks is a "very ordinary looking man," gives an interesting account of Piatt's Zouaves, who he says are "the poorest apologies for soldiers I ever saw--on drill their movements are perfectly comical, and as to their principles, there is no gentleman among them."
    - Charleston, October 24, 1861
      In this letter, Tenney's romance with Addie intensifies.
    - Charleston, December 12, 1861
      Tenney has a long discussion of what he terms "irreparable harm" to the loyal people by the removal of Gen. Fremont (John Charles).
    - Parkersburg, Va. (W. Va.), December 11, 1861
      Tenney is in a cabin of the Decatur. He writes a love letter to Addie, with indications that his regiment soon will lose its view of Ohio and head for "the wilds of Virginia, possibly Romney."
    - Green Spring Run, B.& O. Railroad, December 14, 1861
      Green Spring Run--B & O. Railroad-Tenney picturesquely describes the railroad trip from Parkersburg, traveling in a low freight car, passing through thirteen tunnels in twenty-seven miles. One tunnel was 7/8ths of a mile long, a journey which took them through rough terrain. He also details a new use for Mecca (Ohio) oil in making a bombshell, and discusses military actions of Generals' McClellan (George Brinton) and Halleck (Henry Wager) and the withdrawal of troops from Central Missouri.
    - Romney, Va. (W.Va.) December 18, 1861
      Tenney is lonely because he has not heard from Addie. He finds Romney a "veritable Secesh town," and he expects a fight within a few days with 20,000 Rebels 17 miles from town and General Rosecrans (William Starke) poised to take command.
  - Charles Tenney Letters, January- June, 1862, 27 letters
    Twenty seven letters from January through June, 1862 describe Tenney's movements with his regiment from Romney through the Shenandoah Valley, including vivid account of Battle of Kernstown in which he was wounded. Tenney 's romance with Addie intensifies and he proposes marriage. He describes day-to day camp activities, including living conditions and cooking preparations. He laments resignation from the army of many Ohio officers and indicates next movement of troops will be toward Fredericksburg.
    - Romney, Va. (W. Va.), January 1, 1862
      Tenney is sad because mail has been scarce, but he goes on in depth about the "peculiar sort of excitement in standing picket guard" and includes some incidents in which he was involved.
    - Romney, January 1, 1862
      Tenney happily reports he has received Addie's letter and points out to her, apparently in answer to her inquiry, that he has never been intoxicated and has foresworn all use of tobacco, alcohol and playing cards.
    - Camp Keys, Romney, January 9, 1862
      Tenney tells of four inches of snow and of fighting at [Blew's Gap], sixteen miles from Romney, with Federals breaking and running. However, Tenney did not participate because he was on picket guard.
    - Patterson's Creek Station, January 12, 1862
      Tenney describes a 24-mile retreat from Romney and Springfield toward Cumberland.
    - Patterson's Crreek Station, cont., January 12, 1862
      Tenney speaks of hundreds of rumors circulating and tells of having a dress parade in which they were told to prepare to march.
    - Letter continued, January 11, 1862
      Tenney left Romney at midnight, marched eight miles to Springfield (W.Va.) over muddy roads until midnight; at daybreak continued seven miles to Frankford and then to Patterson's Creek Station on the B. & O. Railroad where they are encamped in 6 inches of snow and mud. He concludes with his attempt to write poetry.
    - Letter, January 13, 1862
      Tenney makes an ardent declaration of love to Addie.
    - Letter, January 15, 1862
      Tenney writes an affectionate letter in which he describes Addie's brother Hal's temporary elevation to command of the company. He mentions his sketching and says he will send some sketches of members of the mess. Tenney calls his position a strong one as described by General Lander (Frederick West).
    - Camp Kelly, Va., January 18, 1862
      Tenney describes his deep love for Addie despite his lack of an elevated position in life and says he waits anxiously for her response.
    - Camp Kelly, Va., January 25, 1862
      Tenney tells Addie not to feel guilty about writing him on a Sunday as "there is an old adage--there are no Sundays in war."
    - Camp Kelly, Va., January 30, 1862
      Tenney writes a long and devout love letter with mention that Gen. McClellan has dampened his hopes for a furlough, but thinks he may come home in July if Winchester is taken before then.
    - [Paw Paw] Tunnel, February
      Tenney is three miles from [Paw Paw] tunnel on the railroad in tents. He requests a miniature of Addie.
    - Camp Tyler, February 23, 1862
      Tenney is near the [PawPaw] Tunnel. He muses to Addie about their romance and how wearily the time passes for him. He describes Washington's birthday celebration the previous day with "arches of evergreen, flags raised, and tents wreathed and decorated in a tasteful manner." The Brigade, consisting of the 7th and 29th Ohio, 110th Pa., 7th Indiana and 1st Va. Regiments, was reviewed by General Lander, who said the "7th is the best regiment in his department." However, Tenney adds, all the best officers in the regiment are resigning and going home. Tenney thinks resignations are due to the fact that the regiment head, Maj. Gen. Erastus Barnard Tyler, is a "ruined and unprincipled head."
    - Camp Tyler, February 26, 1862
      Tenney gives details of his day. He says he likes to receive home papers, but asks to withhold sending books as they are too hard to transport.
    - Camp Tyler, February 26, 1862
      This item is excerpted from a letter to the editor of an unnamed newspaper in which Tenney writes that many of the best officers of the "Noble Seventh" regiment of Ohio are resigning. He asks if any of the readers might know where the difficulty lies.
    - Camp Tyler February 28, 1862
      Tenney describes to Addie his family background and his religious beliefs.
    - Camp Tyler, March 3, 1862
      Tenney describes the ceremony surrounding the funeral of Gen. Lander and the "Noble 7th's" part in it. He asks Addie to marry him.
    - Camp Shields, Va., March 21, 1862
      Tenney briefly notes skirmishes at Cedar Creek and vividly describes in detail what it is like to participate in a bombardment at Strasburg.
    - Camp Shields, March 25, 1862
      Tenney describes realistically and in great detail his participation in the Battle of Kernstown where he suffered a contusion on his right arm. He pictures battlefield scenes and says Col. Tyler (Erastus Barnard) "has retrieved his character as a colonel, but he is Tyler yet."
    - Camp Woodstock, Va., April 7, 1862
      Tenney protests an embargo on sending mail. He says skirmishes continue everyday and quotes from a talk by a chaplain which he thinks warrants attention--"The cardinal sins of the army are--intemperance, profanity, murmuring and robbery. These, sooner or later, will bite like a serpent and sting like an adder."
    - Camp Tyler, April 9, 1862
      Tenney gives intensifying protestations of love to Addie and says there has been snow and hail the last three days.
    - Camp Tyler, April 11, 1862, , one letter, on stationary with the printed poem, "The Soldier's Dream"
      Tennney says he has heard official counts of what he describes as Union victories and tells of contradictions in the term "glorious victories." He lists numerous rumors flying about in camp concerning various military victories and defeat.
    - Camp near New Market, Va., April 22, 1862
      Tenney has left Edinburg on the 17th and arrived at New Market that night. He has a severe cold and tells of an amusing argument in which he tries to convert young southern girl to the Yankee cause.
    - New Market, April 28, 1862, one letter
      Tenney comments favorably on Addie's new school teaching career. He glories over the beautiful spring and reminds her that he will be 21 years old soon.
    - New Market, May 9, 1862
      Tenney muses over his sixth birthday present years ago, a copy of Emerson's First Book of Arithmetic. He intimates that his own sister writes to him only because she wants money.
    - New Market, May 11, 1862
      Tenney writes that his group will start a march tomorrow for Fredericksburg. He says several officers have resigned because tents are being taken away for a month, and they must sleep in the open.
    - Luray Court House, June 5, 1862
      Tenney makes bitter and extensive comments on General Shield's treatment of soldiers in the Valley Campaign because of his "personal ambition." He describes illness of soldiers and their pitiful conditions and tells of the march through the Valley to Fredericksburg and back. He also gives a review of the troops by Abraham Lincoln.
    - Camp near Luray, June 13, 1862
      Tenney reports he was not at the Battle of Port Republic having remained at Luray Court House. He gives his opinions on what religious attitudes Addie should teach her pupils, saying, "I think I should not compel them to read or learn the Bible, but by kind teachings apparently directed to the entire school, but pertinent to their case, teach them Bible truths."
    - Five Miles South of Manassas Junction, June 29, 1862, one letetr
      Tenney describes a march from Front Royal. He tells of discipline he received for walking on the railroad tracks, and vividly writes of a bad storm in camp the previous evening.
  - Charles Tenney Letters, July-December 1862, 18 letters
    Eighteen letters from July through December of 1862 take Tenney from Alexandria, Va. to Warrenton, Va., then on an incursion into Maryland, and finally to Harper's Ferry. Along the way he participates with his regiment in the battles at Cedar Mountain, Antietam and South Mountain. The letters contain many colorful descriptions of the landscape, sketches and details of his camps, including daily living-recipes for cooking, his opinions of generals and newspapers. The romance with Addie becomes even more poignant as he writes to her father with a request for her hand in marriage.
    - Alexandria, Va., July 4, 1862
      Tenney says he tried for a furlough but Sec. Of War has prohibited them. He discusses at length his opinions on why Catholics do not permit their children to read the Bible and describes the Fourth of July celebration with gun salutes from Arlington Heights.
    - Alexandria, July 7, 1862
      .Tenney writes a long letter to Addie's father in which he describes his character and proclaims his love for Addie. He then requests her hand in marriage, asking for a reply.
    - Alexandria, July 14, 1862, one letter and small drawing
      In a good letter, Tenney minutely describes the actual set up of his camp with a small drawing. He shows the interior of his tent and its accoutrements. Tenney then adds four recipes, including fried bread, fried crackers, coffee for one, and blackberry stew. He also continues with a description of daily camp life.
    - Warrenton, Va., July 26, 1862
      Tenney marches to Warrenton, describing the city as a "beautiful little place but rebel to the core--what a blighting curse is secession--rebellion to a great and good government. The first secessionist was Satan."
    - Cedar Mountain, August 13, 1862
      Tenney says he escaped Cedar Mountain battle without a scratch. The 7th Regiment went in with 290 men and came out with 104, and Tenney lists some names of friends killed and wounded He also tells of his part in the battle.
    - Culpeper Court House August 18, 1862
      Tenney notes to Addie that he wrote to her father requesting permission to marry and has received an affirmative reply. He gives a long analysis of his feelings about General McClellan and comments on expectations of foreign aid.
    - Camp in Maryland near Georgetown, September 5, 1862
      Tenney describes a long move to Maryland, giving details of enemy encounters at Centreville and Fairfax Court House. He also tells of the deaths of Generals Stevens (Isaac Ingalls) and Kearney (Philip) at Chantilly. Tenney says, "General Pope has very poorly met the expectations of the nation," and he rejoices in General McClellan's appointment as commander of the Army of the Potomac.
    - Near Rockville, Md., September 9, 1862
      Tenney is in line of a battle two miles above Rockville, Md. He tells of daily routine in the field and describes its characteristics. He also mentions some "obnoxious" General George Sears Greene, who took command of Cedar Mountain after the wounding of Generals Auger (Christopher Colon) and Geary (John White.)
    - Near Harper's Ferry, Va., September 21, 1862
      Tenney gives a detailed and graphic description of Battle of Antietam, including his part in a bayonet charge. He tells of the dead lying in heaps, the 7th holding its own against A.P. Hill's entire division, and panic in the Union brigade. He also describes the horrors he encounters while traversing the field the day after the battle.
    - Blue Ridge Mountains near Harper's Ferry, September 25, 1862
      Tenney describes the location as one a "great natural beauty. As far as romance goes, this is the most interesting place we have been in." He tells of his arrival in Harper's Ferry and gives a description of the results of the action in the town. He defends General McClellan's actions and gives a long dissertation on role of N.Y. Tribune in its "indiscriminate" attacks on McClellan. Tenney also explains why the love of country should be paramount to the love of God.
    - Loudon Heights September 26, 1862
      Tenney writes to Minnie (Addie's sister) describing recent troop movements and battles. He points out that "Maryland is free from Rebel tread, though polluted by Rebel dead."
    - Loudon Heights, September 30, 1862
      Tenney calls Col. Miles (D.S.) surrender at Harper's Ferry the most disgraceful thing of the campaign. He talks of General Geary's taking command at Harper's Ferry and describes General Green as being "very cool and collected in the field" at Antietam. Tenney comments on the Emancipation Proclamation, discusses attempts by Union Army to cut off Confederates from Richmond and indicates disdain for England's recognition of Confederate States.
    - Unknown Location, October 15, 1862
      Tenney remarks on Addie's brother Hal's promotion to Colonel. He describes an 8 by 10-foot log house he and others are building for accommodations. Tenney also gives a lengthy description of why General Pope was defeated on the Rappahannock, including a character analysis of Pope and the Southern Generals Jackson and Lee.
    - Harper's Ferry, October 21, 1862
      Tenney writes a tender letter with Addie's portrait placed on his Bible. As his regiment proceeds to Hillsborough presumably to prevent the enemy from leaving the Valley, Tenney remains in camp because of an illness. He quotes his favorite lines of Byron, but returns to politics by giving thanks that the Vallandigham (Clement Laird) has been defeated in run for Governor of Ohio. Tenney decries political influence at the War Department and its impact on Union Generals' movements, saying "It has almost ruined our Republic."
    - Harper's Ferry, November 7, 1862
      Tenney writes from Provost Marshall's office and says his brigade has moved from Loudon Heights to Bolivar Heights, where he is assigned clerk to Captain Church Howe at General Sedgewick's (John) staff. Tenney thinks the regiment may remain there for the winter.
    - Provost's Office, November 15, 1862
      The letter complains of poor health due to liver complaint.
    - Provost's Office, November 25, 1862
      Tenney says his health is better, but he sounds out Adelaide's opinion on whether he should request a discharge. He remarks on McClellan's removal and assesses General Burnside's prospects for success.
  - Charles Tenney Letters, undated, 12 undated letters
    Twelve undated letters in the collection include several on interesting Union stationary. One comments on the unfinished Washington monument, "a noble tribute from a million souls." Another one is from near Luray, Va., where Tenney reports General Jackson is said to have shot the "only Union man in the neighborhood." One letter describes the pastoral beauty and romance of the countryside near Orkney Springs and White Sulphur Springs, and another strongly comments on John C. Breckinridge, "the most consummate traitor of them all."
  - Charles Tenney Letters, Additions January- May, 1862, Journal papers bound by thread
    The Tenney collection also includes a journal Tenney kept from January through the middle of May 1862. The papers, bound together by thread, deal primarily with an account of troop movements, most of which are described in greater detail in his frequent letters to Adelaide Case. Stationary on which the journal is written includes many colorful Union drawings, quotations and some poetry. In an entry dated May 4, he also gives an interesting description of a visit to "The Harrison Cave," a beautiful grotto near Harrisonburg, Va., which is by way of being spoiled because so many visitors are breaking off pieces of stalactites and stalagmites for souvenirs.
    - Portrait of Adelaide Case, n.d.
- Adelaide Case Letters 1861-1864, 59 letters
  - Adelaide Case Letters, 1861, 14 letters
    Fourteen letters written in 1861 convey the tentative beginnings of Adelaide's romance with Charles Tenney. She appears to be hesitant to become too involved and urges him to think of her as a "loving sister." Addie describes her devoted relationship with her brother Hal, who also is in the service. She tells Charles of activities in the town of Mecca, Ohio since both he and Hal have left.
    These letters are arranged chronologically.
    - Mecca, Oh., January 18, 1861
      At this point, Addie and Charlie are referring to each other as "dear brother and sister," and Addie inquires tactfully why Charlie and his real sister have a troubled relationship.
    - Mecca, June 6, 1861
      Addie addresses the letter as "Dear friend," and again emphasizes that Charlie and she should remain purely "friends." She adds that she thinks tintypes should not be exchanged unless a couple is engaged.
    - Mecca, August 10, 1861
      Addie still addresses the letter as "Dear Friend." She remarks that the 19th Ohio regiment returned to Mecca "last week," but wishes it had been the "noble 7th," which includes both Charlie and her brother Hal. Addie mentions the reason she had agreed to correspond with Charlie came from the remark he made before leaving, "My home is not what a home should be," which impressed her deeply. Addie signs her letter as "Yours in pure friendship."
    - Mecca, September 10, 1861
      Addie has heard Charles participated in a fight and desperately wants a letter. She says the newspaper listed brother Hal as a casualty but later contradicted it. Addie also comments, "suspense is almost as bad as reality."
    - Mecca, September 26, 1861
      Addie has received his engraving of Camp Denison. She comments on her feelings of worthlessness during the war and beseeches Charlie to write. She progresses to "Affectionately--Addie G. Case."
    - Mecca, October 1, 1861
      On an attractive flag stationary, Addie writes it is a beautiful day, but war has robbed Mecca of much of its beauty because of its loss of young men. She has high praise for her brother Hal, gives some counsel to Charlie on his future life plans, and she says she is "pleased he intends to make a man of himself."
    - Mecca, October 3, 1861